Guide to the UH Law Center Records
University of Houston Libraries
UH Law Center Records
1930-2009
2009-011
University of Houston. Law Center
3.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
These records contain 2 boxes and 1 oversize folder relating to the University of Houston Law Center. A significant portion of this material was given to the archives from the university Print Plant.
Historical Note:
Officially opened in 1947 with 28 students and one professor, the Law Center has seen many changes. In 1950 the Bates College of Law moved from temporary classrooms to the basement of the M.D. Anderson Library. Full accreditation from the American Bar Association came on February 24, 1953. [1] Ground was broken for the current facility, consisting of three buildings, in 1969. When it became obvious that additional funds were needed to complete the Bates College of Law a grant of $400,000 was made available. Krost Hall, part of the UH Law Center, was named in honor of this grant.
Today, the primary objective of the Law Center is to provide a context for excellence in legal education and research. It seeks to provide broad, but intensive, training in the legal profession with students exposed to a variety of perspectives on law and legal systems. Students are expected to develop familiarity with contemporary law and the legal skills necessary to function as competent, ethical professionals. The Law Center emphasizes neither a theoretical nor a practical view of law, but believes that both are integral to legal education.
During the 1990s, the Law Center experienced dramatic qualitative and quantitative growth. The student body consists of more than 1,000 individuals drawn from all parts of the country in a highly competitive admissions program. Many law students have graduate degrees or professional recognition in other disciplines. The student body's quality, professional achievement, geographic origin, and ethnic diversity represent strengths of the Law Center. These strengths result in placement of graduates in major law firms in Houston and throughout the country.
Instruction is conducted primarily by full-time law faculty. Many are nationally recognized experts in fields such as health law, intellectual property law, international law, energy law, environmental law, commercial law, family law, Constitutional law and tax law. The faculty is supported by a select group of adjunct professors from the Houston bar, one of the major legal communities in the country. This combined faculty offers a broad range of professional experience and expertise.
[1] Patrick J. Nicholson, In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston (Houston, TX: Pacesetter Press, 1977), 277.
[2] UH Through Time: Colleges, available from http://info.lib.uh.edu/sca/digital/time/index.html. 12 August 2009.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston. Law Center
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
These records contain 2 boxes and 1 oversize folder relating to the University of Houston Law Center. A significant portion of this material was given to the archives from the university Print Plant. Material includes certificates, registration material, correspondence, course information, event programs and flyers, reports, newsletters, stationary, and published material. This collection is arranged alphabetically by department, program, or subject title. Material ranges in date from the 1930s to 2009.
Detailed List of Contents
- A.A. White Dispute Resolution Center (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Albertus Magnus, December 1976-Spring 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual Law & Gala Auction (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Arbitrators (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Arrival Awards (recognizing immigrant achievement) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Career Services Office (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Center for Children Law & Policy (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Certificates (Box 1, Folder 8)
- College of Law (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Environmental Liability Law Report, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Graduate Legal Studies Program (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Health Law News (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Health Law & Policy Institute (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Health Law & Policy Institute - Brochures (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Honor Code (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Houston Lawyers Registered Under New Act, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- HHP Today Law, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Houston Bar Association (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Houston Journal of International Law (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Houston Law Review (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Immigration Clinic Update, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Institute for Energy, Law & Enterprise (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Institute for Higher Education Law and Goverance (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Institute for Intellectual Property & Information Law (Box 1, Folder 24)
- International Law Institute (Box 1, Folder 25)
- James Berry (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Law, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Law Alumni Association (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Law Briefcase Magazines (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Law Center - Admissions (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Law Center (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
- Law Commencement Programs (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Law Fraternity (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Law Fund (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Law Handbook, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Law Libraries (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Law Library Newsletters, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Law Summer School in Mexico (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Legalese (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Memo from the Dean (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Mexican Legal Studies Program, 1980-1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Miscelaneous (Box 2, Folder 11)
- National Association for Law Placement (Box 2, Folder 12)
- National College of Criminal Defense Lawyers & Pub. Def. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- National College of District Attorneys, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- National College of District Attorneys, Bulletin/Academic Catalog, 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- National College of District Attorneys, Certficates (Box 2, Folder 16)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- National College of District Attorneys, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- National College of District Attorneys - Stationery (Box 2, Folder 25)
- NCAA Update, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Obiter Dictum (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Pro Facto, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Student Bar Association (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Stationery (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
- Texas Law Institute on Costal and Marine Resources (Box 2, Folder 32)
- The Advance Sheet, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- The Dean’s Report (Box 2, Folder 34)
- The Docket, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- The Practical Prosecutor, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- The Texas Law Institute Reporter, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- The Unlimited Deduction for Charitable Contrib, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Trial Advocacy Institute (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Update on Health, 2002-2009 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Certificate, undated (Drawer F.9, Ovs folder 10)